Finding Aid for the California State University, Long Beach. Center for Women's Studies ACLU Lawsuit Records LSC.2201
UCLA Library Special Collections
California State University, Long Beach. Center for Women's Studies ACLU lawsuit records
1974-1991
UCLA Library Special Collections
California State University, Long Beach. Center for Women's Studies
LSC.2201
0.6 linear feet (2 boxes)
The documents contained in this collection range from 1974-1991, focusing on issues facing the Women's Studies Program at California State Univeristy, Long Beach (CSULB) in the 1980s. In 1982, 13 faculty members and three students filed a lawsuit with the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) against CSULB, charging the University with violations of the First and Fourth Amendments. Formats of materials include meeting notes, court records, pamphlets, newsletters, press clippings, reports, correspondence, financial and donor information, and education files.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, 2013.
General
The June L. Mazer Lesbian Archive at UCLA is an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW), and the UCLA Library. These collections expand the pool of primary source materials available to researchers and to the community at large. This partnership was initiated by CSW and is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) to inventory, organize, preserve, and digitize more than eighty Mazer collections pertaining to lesbian and feminist activism and writings.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9990023653606533
Custodial History
This collection was donated to the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives circa the 1990s by an unknown source.
Biographical / Historical
California State University, Long Beach (CSULB) was founded in 1949. Its Center for Women's Studies was created in 1972. During the 1980s, with the rising tide of conservative and traditional values, the Women's Studies Program was a constant target of harassment for teaching subjects on feminism and lesbians. These attacks came to a peak in 1982 when the Vice-President of CSULB, with the assistance of other anti-feminist persons and associations of interest, announced they would restructure the Women's Studies Program to include more traditional views of femininity. The restructuring included removing the program director, Dr. Sondra Hale, and Women's Center director, Denise Wheeler. This would be the catalyst for the 1982 lawsuit filed by the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) on behalf of the Women's Studies Program.
Scope and Contents
The documents contained in this collection range from 1974-1991, focusing on issues facing the Women's Studies Program at California State Univeristy, Long Beach (CSULB) in the 1980s. The collection contains materials relating to the Women's Studies staff and faculty's legal fight over control of the department, particularly the 1982 lawsuit in which 13 faculty members and three students filed a suit with the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) against CSULB, charging the University with violations of the First and Fourth Amendments. Materials include CSULB Women's Studies clippings, "Sandra Hale v. Board of Trustees" materials, financial records, ACLU Foundation Account materials, correspondence, and lawsuit press clippings related to this court case circa 1982. The majority of materials in the collection concern the coordinated attacks by conservative groups against the CSULB Women's Studies Program, in the name of traditional values. These repeated attacks targeted courses related to feminism and lesbian studies, along with their staff and faculty.
Organization and Arrangement
Materials maintain their existing order.
Related Materials
California State University, Long Beach, Center for Women's Studies records (LSC 1817). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Women's studies -- United States.; June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives.; June L. Mazer Lesbian Archive at UCLA.; California State University, Long Beach. Center for Women's Studies
- Community updates, Women's Studies lawsuit, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Ad hoc committee report on Women's Studies, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous, 1983-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- California Faculty Association (CFA v. CSULB), 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Fresno Free College Foundation, Long Beach Defense Fund (UPC), 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Women's Studies steering committee, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- ACLU Foundation Account, Women's Studies Defense Fund, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Community coalition, Women's Studies lawsuit, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Women's Studies steering committee, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Press clippings, Women's Studies lawsuit, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- The Eagle Forum documents, Women's Studies lawsuit, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Women's Studies defense committee cash account, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)